We live on one level of existence, but there are others.
除了我们生活的这个层次  还有其他的
These hidden dimensions of reality are everywhere.
到处充满了隐藏着的其他维度
Far away, across the light years.
从许多光年以外
Beneath our feet.
到我们的脚下
And even inside you and me.
甚至在我们的体内
We are made of atoms.
我们由原子组成
There are more atoms in your eye,
我们眼睛中的原子数量
than there are stars and all the galaxies
of the known universe
比已知宇宙中所有星系的星星数量还多
The same is true of any solid object
上述情况也适用于任何
larger than the tip of your little finger.
比你的指尖稍大的实体
I'm a collection of three billion, billion, billion
我由30万亿亿亿复杂排列的原子组成
intricately arranged atoms called Neil Degrasse Tyson.
我是名叫尼尔·德葛拉司·泰森的原子组合体
You are a similar collection with a different name.
你们也是一样  只是名字不同
We don't usually think of ourselves this way
我们通常不会这么认为
because that level of reality lies beyond the realm of our senses.
因为这个级别的存在超过了我们感官的范畴
But we're not gonna let that stop us.
但是我们不会就此停止
We can go deeper into the wonder.
我们还要继续探究
Sync and corrections by oykubuyuk
www.addic7ed.com
中文翻译：@SaltyEggPain
宇    宙
时空探险之旅
第 6 集
深入到更深层次
Deeper, Deeper, Deeper Still
Atoms let matter do funny things.
原子使所有事情变得有生气
To understand water, you need to know what its atoms are doing.
要了解水 你需要知道它的原子规律
Every molecule of water is composed
每个水分子都是由
of two tiny hydrogen atoms
两个小小的氢原子
attached to a larger oxygen atom.
附着在一个大的氧原子上组成
That's why we call it H20.
因此我们称之为 一氧化二氢
If it's not too hot or too cold,
如果温度不冷不热
the molecules can slide and tumble past each other.
分子们可以相互翻滚穿行
There's still some stickiness between the molecules,
分子间虽然有一些粘滞性
but not enough to lock them into a rigid solid.
但是不足以让它们变得紧密
That's what makes something a liquid.
这就是液体的特性
The sun warms the water.
太阳将水加热
And with more energy,
给它更多的能量
the molecules move faster.
分子们移动加快
That's all that temperature is.
温度就是这样的
Those molecules are moving fast enough
当分子运到快到足以
to break the weak bonds that hold them to their neighbors.
打破彼此间脆弱的联系时
That's evaporation.
就是蒸发
The air we breathe is made of
我们呼吸的空气
nitrogen and oxygen molecules
就是由氮和氧的分子组成
with a scattering of water vapor and carbon dioxide.
再加一些水蒸气和二氧化碳
Incoming!
小心
That's condensation.
那是冷凝
A dewdrop is the momentary triumph
露珠就是冷凝战胜蒸发
of condensation over evaporation.
的胜利果实
And while it lasts,
这种现象持续下去
it's a little cosmos with its own worlds...
它就是一个小宇宙 包含它自己的世界
creatures, drama.
生物 戏剧性的事情
To explore the far-flung realms of this dewdrop
为了探索这滴露珠的广阔领域
we're gonna need a ship.
我们需要一艘船
One with twin engines...
配上两种引擎
science and imagination.
科学和想象力
That's a single-celled paramecium,
那是单细胞的草履虫
one of a multitude of skilled hunter-warriors
众多娴熟的猎人之一
that roam the dewdrop.
在露珠中游荡
But they, too, are hunted.
但是它们也是猎物
The Dileptus. The paramecium's mortal enemy.
长颈虫  草履虫的死敌
The paramecium might get lucky and score a direct hit.
草履虫或许可以幸运的直接击杀
Even if it doesn't,
就算不能
the recoil from the barrage will put some distance
齐射攻击造成的后座力拉开了
between the paramecium and its attacker.
草履虫与攻击者之间的距离
What can I say?
没什么可说的
That's life in the dewdrop.
那就是露珠内的生活
That little guy is tardigrade,
那个小家伙是水熊虫
an animal smaller than the head of a pin.
一种比针尖还小的动物
Don't underestimate them.
可别小看它
Tardigrades have been living on this planet
水熊虫在这个星球上的历史
a lot longer than we have.
比我们的还长久
About 500 million years.
大约5亿年
For every one of us,
和我们的数量比例
there's at least a billion of them.
至少是1比10亿
They can make a living anywhere on earth.
它们可以在地球上任何地方生存
In the frigid peaks of the tallest mountains,
在最高的寒冷的山峰顶端
in the cauldrons of erupting volcanoes,
在喷发的火山口里
and in the deep ocean vents at the bottom of the sea.
在大洋的底部
Tardigrades are so tough,
水熊虫是如此的坚强
they can survive naked
它们可以在
in the vacuum of space.
真空中生存
They've survived all five
它们经历了最近
of the most recent mass extinctions on this planet.
5次的大灭绝
A visitor from another world could be forgiven
如果外星人认为地球是水熊虫的世界
for thinking of earth as the planet of the tardigrades.
那是绝对可以原谅的
If we're ever gonna get to the bottom of this dewdrop
better get a move on.
如果还要看这滴露珠的其他地方 最好继续往前走
Every leaf and tiny clump of moss
每片叶子和苔藓
has hundreds of thousands
都有成千上万的
of microscopic mouths called Stomata.
显微镜才能看见的嘴巴 称为气孔
Plants breathe through them,
植物通过它们呼吸
taking in carbon dioxide
吸入二氧化碳
and exhaling the oxygen that we need to live.
呼出我们赖以生存的氧气
The plants can survive without us.
地球上可以没有我们
But we and all the other animals...
但是我们还有其他动物
we'd be toast without them.
离开它们就死翘翘了
The plants make food out of sunlight.
地球通过阳光获取食物
We animals can't do that.
我们动物做不到
To see how they do it,
想看它们是怎么做到的
we have to go deeper,
我们还要潜的更深
make ourselves about a thousand times smaller
把我们变小大约1千倍
to get into their treasure house,
才能进入它们的宝库
the place where they keep the good stuff...
它们把好东西都藏在里面
the chlorophyll.
叶绿素
That's the molecule
也是个分子
that converts sunlight into energy.
把阳光转换成能量
Every one of those rectangles is a plant cell.
每个长方形都是一个植物细胞
And those tiny green vehicles
还有那些小绿车
are its energy factories.
都是它的能量工厂
If we could steal their trade secrets,
如果我们可以窃取它们的商业机密
it would trigger a new industrial revolution.
又能带来一次崭新的工业革命
But to spy on them,
但是要偷窥它们
we're gonna need to go deeper still.
我们还要潜的更深
What alien world has the ship of the imagination
想象之舟这次又要将我们带去
carried us to this time?
哪个截然不同的世界呢
It's the cosmos...
它是个宇宙
Contained within a dewdrop.
包含在露珠内的宇宙
We're on an industrial espionage mission.
我们现在做的就是工业间谍活动
If we can penetrate the trade secrets
如果想刺探叶绿体的商业机密
of the manufacturing process in that chloroplast,
叶绿体里的制作过程
let's just say our whole future hangs in the balance.
就当我们的全部未来就靠它了
This chloroplast is using sunlight
叶绿体利用阳光
to break water molecules
将水分子
into atoms of hydrogen and oxygen.
分解成氢原子和氧原子
It combines the hydrogen with carbon dioxide
将氢气与二氧化碳结合
to make sugar,
产生糖
and releases the oxygen as a waste product.
将氧气作为废气排出
To see how it happens, we have to go even deeper,
要一探究竟 我们还要潜的更深
get even smaller.
变得更小
We're talking atomic scale.
小到原子级别
Bingo.
成功了
This assembly line is the heart
这条流水线是分子工业基地
of the molecular industrial complex.
的核心
At the molecular level,
在分子这个级别
things happen too fast for us to see.
速度快到我们看不到
So we'll have to slow them down
所以我们必须让它们慢下来
about a billion times.
放慢10亿倍
Those larger molecules are carbon dioxide.
那些大分子就是二氧化碳
Each one of them is made
每一个分子
of one carbon and two oxygen atoms.
由1个碳原子和2个氧原子组成
When sunlight strikes a green molecule of chlorophyll,
当阳光照射叶绿素的分子
it sets in motion a series of chemical reactions,
产生一系列的化学反应
breaking apart water molecules
分解水分子
and freeing energetic electrons.
释放活泼的电子
And that's just the day shift,
这只是白班的活
when sunlight supplies the incoming stream of energy.
只在日光注入能量时工作
There's a second shift that works day and night
还有一组不分昼夜的工作
using the solar energy kept in reserve.
利用预留的太阳能工作
The energy of the free electrons is put to work,
自由电子的能量开始工作了
combining carbon dioxide with hydrogen from the water.
将二氧化碳与水中的氢结合
The end product is sugar,which stores the solar energy.
产生糖  用以储存太阳能
The chloroplast is a three-billion-year-old
叶绿体从事太阳能采集工作
solar energy collector.
达30亿年之久
This sub-microscopic solar battery
微观世界的太阳能电池
is what drives all the forests and the fields
驱动所有的森林 田地
and the plankton of the seas.
海中的浮游生物
And the animals.
还有动物
Including us.
包括我们
The solar-powered biosphere
太阳能的生物圈
collects and processes six times more power
than our entire civilization
比我们整个人类文明收集并处理的能量多出6倍
We understand on a chemical level
我们了解化学层面的
how photosynthesis works.
光合作用工作原理
We can recreate the process in a laboratory.
我们可以在实验室复制这样的过程
But we're not as good at it as plants are.
但是我们做不到植物这么好
And it's not surprising,
这不奇怪
considering nature has been at this for billions of years,
大自然已经干了几十亿年了
and we've only just started.
我们才刚开始
But if we could figure out
如果我们可以知道
the trade secrets of photosynthesis,
光合作用的商业机密
every of other source of energy we depend on today...
如今我们赖以生存的其他形式的能量
coal, oil, natural gas...
煤 石油 天然气
would become obsolete.
都可以淘汰了
Photosynthesis is the ultimate green power.
光合作用是终极绿色能源
It doesn't pollute the air
不会污染大气
and is, in fact, carbon neutral.
事实上 碳中和
Artificial photosynthesis on a big enough scale
人造光合作用可以很大程度上
could reduce the greenhouse effect
减少温室效应
that's driving climate change in a dangerous direction.
温室效应恶化了气候变化
Uh-oh, place is evaporating.
这里开始蒸发了
Time to get out of here.
该撤了
How fleeting is the life of a dewdrop.
露珠的生命一闪即逝
It condenses from thin air in the cool of the night,
在寒冷的夜里从稀薄的空气中凝结而成
only to vanish with the heat of the day.
却在日出之后无影无踪
And what of its inhabitants, the tardigrades?
它的居民怎么办 水熊虫呢
They'll be fine.
没事的
They can go without water for years.
它们可以几年不喝水
It's hard to imagine,
很难想象
but plants covered the surface of the earth
覆盖地球表面的植物
for hundreds of millions of years
几亿年后
before they put forth their first flower.
才开出第一朵花
That was about a hundred million years ago,
大约1亿年前
shortly before the dinosaurs were wiped out.
恐龙灭绝前不久
Our world must've been a relatively
drab-looking place back then,
当时世界的颜色一定很单调
dominated by shades of green and brown.
只有绿色和褐色
Yeah, there were giant trees and ferns and other plant life,
那是有大树和蕨类 还有其他的植物
but not the purple of an iris
但是没有紫色的鸢尾花
or the crimson of a red, red rose.
也没有大红色的玫瑰花
Orchids were among the first flowering species
兰花是最早出现的花之一
to appear on earth, and they're the most diverse.
现在它们有着最多的品种
Darwin was particularly fascinated
达尔文特别痴迷
by the comet orchid of Madagascar,
马达加斯加的彗星兰
a flower whose pollen is hidden at the bottom
这种花的花粉藏在一条又长又细的
of a very long, thin spur.
花径底部
There can be no stronger test of an idea
预测能力是验证一种理论
than its predictive power.
最好的方法
On the basis of his theory of evolution
根据他的物竞天择
through natural selection
的进化论基础
Darwin speculated that somewhere
达尔文推测
on the island of Madagascar, there must live flying insects
在马达加斯加岛上 一定有一种会飞的昆虫
with extraordinarily lengthy tongues,
长着非常长的舌头
ones long enough to reach the pollen.
长的足够接触到那些花粉
No one had ever seen such a beast there,
从没人看过这种动物
but Darwin insisted
但是达尔文坚信
that an animal fitting this description must exist.
肯定有这样的动物存在
Few people at the time believed him.
当时相信他的人不多
It wasn't until more than 50 years later
直到50多年后
that Darwin was proven right.
才证明了达尔文的正确
In 1903, a huge hawk moth, called the Morgan's sphinx
1903年 有一种被称为马岛长喙天蛾的蛾子
was discovered in Madagascar.
在马达加斯加被发现
Attracted by the Comet Orchid's scent,
受到彗星兰花粉香味的吸引
the moth slurps its pollen with its foot-long tongue,
这蛾子用它1英尺长的口器吸食花粉
exactly as Darwin expected it would.
和达尔文预测的一样
It's even more amazing that the
Morgan's sphinx was discovered
更令人惊奇的是 发现这种蛾子时
when you consider that more than 90%
马达加斯加岛上超过90%
of Madagascar's rain forest had been destroyed.
的雨林已经遭到破坏
In the years since Darwin's famous prediction,
在达尔文著名的猜测多年后
this moth species could have easily become extinct
这种蛾子很有可能已经灭绝
with all the others...
就和其他同类一样
every one of them a unique phrase of life's poetry,
它们每一个都是生命诗篇中的独特乐章
written in the atoms by eons of evolution.
由万古的进化写在原子中
Ah, the fragrance of lilacs.
丁香花的芬芳
It's one of those scents
这种香味
that triggers a whole constellation of associations,
让人不禁浮想翩翩
all those junes of long ago.
很久前的每个夏天都是如此
But how does that happen?
怎会如此
How does a smell prompt a movie to
start running in your head?
味道是怎么会让你的头脑中出现影像的
It's not something we can see.
那不是我们能看到的
Could it be a wave of energy, like light?
有可能是象光一样的能量波吗
Or is it some kind of microscopic particle?
还是一种微观粒子呢
It's actually a molecule.
其实它是一种分子
Every odor we can sense, whether it comes from burnt toast
每种味道 不论是来自烤焦的面包
gasoline, or a field of lilacs,
还是汽油 或者一片丁香花
is a cloud of molecules.
都是一大片的分子
These molecules have particular shapes.
这些分子有种特定的形状
When I inhale them,
当我吸入它们时
they stimulate a particular set
of receptor cells in my nose.
它们刺激我鼻子中一组特定的感受细胞
An electrical signal then travels to my brain,
一种电子信号传递到我的大脑
which identifies the scent as lilac.
告诉我这个味道是丁香花的香味
Other scents are carried by different molecules
不同的分子携带不同的味道
with different shapes.
形状各异
But when I smell a flower or the smoke from a campfire
但当我闻到一朵花 或者篝火
or the grease from a motor gear,
或者机器的润滑油
I'm often flooded with memories.
通常是涌现出大量的记忆
Why is it that a simple thing such as the scent of a flower
为什么花香这么简单的东西能够引起
can trigger powerful memories?
强烈的记忆呢
It has to do with the way our brains have evolved.
一定和我们的大脑进化方式有关
Our sense of smell kicks in
当大脑中的嗅神经受到刺激
when the olfactory nerve in our brain is stimulated.
我们的嗅觉开始工作
That nerve is located very close to the amygdala,
这种神经就在扁桃体旁边
a structure that is integral to our experience of emotion.
是我们情感体验的组成部分
It's also very close to the Hippocampus,
也很靠近海马体
which helps us form memories.
产生记忆的地方
The network of neurons that carry the scent signal
神经网络将气味信号
from my nose to my brain has been fine-tuned
从我的鼻子传递到
over hundreds of millions of years of evolution.
我这经过上亿年进化的大脑
It's a survival mechanism that can alert us
这是一种生存机制 给我们发出警告
to danger or guide us to safety.
让我们避开危险
If you you can detect the predator
如果你能提前发觉猎食者
before he's near enough to strike,
在他发动攻击前
or the fire before it traps you in the forest,
或者在被大火困在森林前
you have a much better chance to survive
就会大大增加你的生存几率
and pass on your genes to the next generation.
然后把你的基因传给下一代
That lovely scent from this field of flowers
花田里的迷人芬芳
sets off a unique combination of nerve signals.
发出一组独特的神经信号密码
Only that exact combination can crack the safe
只有这个密码可以打开我们大脑中
where the memory of lilacs is stored inside my brain.
储存关于丁香花的记忆保险箱
Wonder who they're for.
啥味道
Maybe we'll find out later.
我们或许以后会知道
But first, there's another hidden cosmos waiting for us.
但首先 还有一个隐藏着的宇宙等着我们
The plants are softly breathing,
植物们静静的呼吸
inhaling molecules of carbon dioxide
吸入二氧化碳分子
and exhaling molecules of oxygen.
呼出氧气分子
And I'm doing the opposite.
和我相反
Unlike snowflakes and fingerprints,
与雪花和指纹不一样
atoms or molecules of the same kind
同类的原子或分子
are utterly identical to one another.
都是完全的相同
With every breath we take,
每次吸气
we inhale as many molecules as there are stars
我们吸入的分子数量
in all the galaxies in the visible universe.
和已知宇宙的所有星星数量一样多
And every breath we exhale is circulated through the air,
呼出的气体与空气流通交换
and mixed gradually across the continents,
在大地上逐渐混合
it becomes available for others to breathe.
让别人也可以呼吸
Breathe with me.
一起呼吸
We all just inhaled about 100 million molecules
我们大致吸入了1亿的分子
that once passed through the lungs of everyone
这些分子曾经被所有的前人
who ever lived before us.
呼吸过
Think of it... This kind of atomic reincarnation
想想看 这种原子的再生
is another link to our distant ancestors,
将我们与远古的祖先联系在一起
including those who first launched us on our explorations
包括那些最初带领我们
of the unseen universes.
探索未知宇宙的人
These universes are as real as you or me,
这些宇宙就如同你我一样真实
and they surround us.
就在我们的身边
There was a moment when we awakened
曾经我们如梦初醒
to a new way of thinking and seeing.
开始用崭新的方法审视和思考
It happened about 2,500 years ago
那是大约2500年前
on the Greek islands that lie
在希腊的小岛上
between the empires of the east and west.
位于东方与西方文明之间
There, merchants, tourists and sailors freely mingled,
商人 游客 水手们自由的融合
exchanging tales of great kings and gods.
交流各自关于伟人和神的传说
In Ionian cities and towns like Miletus, in what is now Turkey,
在爱奥尼亚有个叫米利都的城市 就是今天的土耳其
the most fundamental elements
一些现代生活的最基本元素
of the way we live now first appeared.
在那里出现了
Here, for the first time,
reenactments of aspects of life
第一次对生活形式的重现
created and executed by professionals
由专业人士创作并演绎
with the expectation of touching something deep
期待可以深深感动
within the hearts of the audience,
观众的内心
or just making them laugh...
或者只是逗他们开心
The first plays, dramas and comedies, were performed.
诞生了第一场演出 戏剧还有喜剧
Here, also, was born a radical new idea:
还有一种极其崭新的概念
Government by the people.
民治政府
The first inklings, imperfect then as now, of a democracy,
从最初模糊的不完美的概念 到如今的民主
and the notion that the ordinary citizen
might possess certain rights
普通民众也可以拥有某些权力的观念
come to us from this time and place.
在那时 在这里诞生萌芽
But in my view, the most revolutionary innovation of all
但在我看来 这个古代世界带给我们的
to come to us from this ancient world was the idea
最革命性的创新观念是
that natural events were neither punishment nor reward
from capricious gods.
自然事件并不是众神给我们的惩罚或奖励
The workings of nature could be explained
大自然的规律不一定要用
without invoking the supernatural.
超自然力量来解释
The first person to express this thought
表达出这种观念的第一人
was a man named Thales.
名叫 泰利斯（希腊哲学家）
When the thunder clapped or the earth quaked,
当闪电或地震时
it was not because something you did had somehow displeased
the very demanding gods.
不是因为我们的所作所为触怒了严厉的众神
No, it was the result of natural processes
只是一种我们可以理解的
that we were capable of understanding.
自然过程的结果
Though none of the books he is
said to have written survive,
尽管没有任何记录他原话的书籍留存下来
Thales kindled a flame that still burns to this day:
泰利斯的思想光芒依然照耀我们
The very idea of cosmos out of chaos,
宇宙运行的井井有条的原因
a universe governed by the order of natural laws
that we can actually figure out.
宇宙由我们可以理解的自然法则控制的这种观念
This is the epic adventure that
began in the mind of Thales.
这种伟大的观念在泰利斯的头脑中萌芽
Only a century following Thales' death,
仅仅在泰利斯身后100年
another genius came along.
又一个天才出现了
And he, more than any other,
他与众不同的是
was the first to discover the existence
第一个发现了
of the hidden universes that surround us.
我们周围未知宇宙的存在
Democritus of Abdera was a true scientist,
来自阿夫季拉的德谟克利特是位真正的科学家
a man with a passionate desire to know the cosmos
充满探索宇宙激情的男人
and to have fun.
也很会享受
This is the man who once said, "a life without parties
他曾说 没有狂欢的生活
would be like an endless road without an end."
就像没有尽头的漫漫长路
You mean, that's it?
这就样吗
That's all there is?
就这么简单吗
Just a bunch of atoms in a void?
只是虚无中的一堆原子
Yep.
然也
Well, think about it.
你想想看
The world has to be made
这个世界必然是
of countless indivisible particles in a void.
由虚无中无数的不可见的微粒组成
Otherwise, nothing could move or grow,
be divided or changed.
否则万物就不会移动 生长 被分离或改变
Without atoms and empty space for them to move in,
如果没有原子和容纳它们的空旷太空的话
the world would be solid, static, and dead.
这个世界会变得铁板一块 死气沉沉
so don't be sad, my friends.
别伤心了 少年
Just think of the infinite possibilities
想想那无尽的可能性吧
that arise from different arrangements of those atoms.
由那些原子排列组合所带来的可能性
Here's to the atoms
向这杯中
in this cup and in this wine...
还有酒中的原子们致敬
And to the laughter they make possible.
还有它们带来的欢乐
Dispersed through the Clay of the cup
遍布酒杯的泥土
are microscopic mineral grains,
都是用显微镜才能看到的矿物微粒
different kinds of crystals,
晶体的一种
each with its own distinctive atomic architecture.
每个都有与众不同的原子结构
Mineral structures are exquisite,
矿物结构很精妙
but they have a limited repertoire.
但是它们的结构形式有限
A grain of quartz is a lattice of the same three atoms
一粒石英就是一个由3个相同原子组成的晶格集合体
repeated, without variation, over and over again.
没有变化 不断重复
Even a relatively complex mineral lattice like topaz,
即使是相对复杂的矿物晶格 比如黄宝石
composed of ten or so atoms,
由10个左右的原子组成
can only repeat the identical atomic structure
也只是相同的原子结构
again and again.
不断重复
To leave the matter to another dimension,
为了转换到另一个维度
to free it from the lattice prison of endless repetition,
为了将它从不断重复的晶格束缚中释放
you need an atom that can bond in all directions
with other atoms like itself
你需要一个可以从任何方向与其他原子相结合的原子
as well as with atoms of different kinds.
它也要能与其他不同的原子相结合
Behold the carbon atom...
看 碳原子
the essential element for life on earth.
地球上生命不可缺少的元素
Why?
为啥
Carbon is special because it can bond with
up to four other atoms at a time.
碳之所以特殊是因为它可以一次与最多4种原子结合
It can connect with many different kinds of atoms,
它可以与许多其他种类的原子结合
as well as other carbon atoms.
也包括其他碳原子
It can curl into rings
它可以弯曲成环状
and string together into chains,
也可以连成一条线
building molecules far more
complex than any crystal.
组成远比任何一种晶体都复杂的分子
No other atom has the same flexibility.
其它原子都没有这种灵活性
Even atoms that have similar chemical properties,
就算拥有类似化学属性的原子也不行
like silicon,
比如 硅
can't form the amazing variety of molecules built on carbon.
也无法像碳这样组成丰富多样的分子
The carbon-based molecules we call proteins,
这种碳基分子 我们称为 蛋白质
the molecules of life,
组成生命的分子
contain literally hundreds of thousands of atoms.
包含了成千上万的原子
Carbon atoms are the backbone of the molecules
that make every living thing on earth,
碳原子是世界上一切生物分子的支柱
including us.
包括我们
That's the difference between rocks and living things.
这就是岩石和生物的区别
Life can make enormous molecules
生命可以制造出大量的
of stunning size and complexity,
有着惊人体积和复杂性的分子
freeing matter to improvise,
自由自在地随机应变
evolve,
进化
and even love.
甚至 爱
Take it easy, dad.
放轻松
He never actually touched her.
他并没有真的碰到的她
In everyday life on our world,
日常生活中
on the scale of atoms,
以原子这个层面上来说
material objects never really touch.
物体绝对不会接触
Each atom has a tiny nucleus at its center,
每个原子的中心都有一个原子核
surrounded by an electron cloud
of lines of force.
被力线电子云所包围
As the atoms approach each other,
当原子彼此接近时
the boy's electron clouds
男孩的电子云
push away the girl's.
推开女孩的电子云
More than 99.9% of the matter of any atom
超过99.9%的原子物质
is concentrated in its nucleus.
集中在它的原子核中
The nucleus is surrounded by an electron cloud
原子核被电子云包围
which produces an invisible field of force,
电子云形成无形的力场
and acts like a shock absorber.
就像减震器
The configuration of the electron cloud
电子云的结构
determines the nature of an element.
决定了元素的本质
In the ordinary course of things here on earth,
以地球上物质的正常情况来说
the nuclei never touch.
原子核不会彼此接触
We have a sensation of touching,
我们有接触的感觉
but that's really just our invisible force fields
那只不过是看不见的力场
overlapping and repelling each other.
相互重叠的同时相互排斥
The nucleus is very small
原子核非常小
compared to the rest of the atom.
相较于原子的其他部分
If an atom were the size of this cathedral,
如果原子像这个教堂这么大
its nucleus would be the size of that mote of dust.
原子核的尺寸也就是那粒灰尘的大小
An atom is mostly empty space.
原子的大部分是空旷的空间
To understand the nature of matter,
为了理解事物的本质
we have to go deeper still,
我们要去更深的地方
to a place 100,000 times smaller than the atom:
去一个比原子还小10万倍的地方
Its nucleus.
它的原子核
The simplest and most plentiful atom
in the cosmos is hydrogen.
宇宙中最简单 但又最丰富的原子是氢原子
Its nucleus is a single proton,
它的原子核只有一个质子
which makes hydrogen element number one.
所以它在元素周期表中位于第一位
The clouds that surround it
围绕它的云
are the realms where the atom's lone electron
is permitted to roam.
是它唯一的电子可以运行的范围
What happens when you have a nucleus with two protons?
原子核有两个质子时会是什么情况
Protons repel each other.
质子相互排斥
In order to hold them together in a nucleus,
为了让它们保持在原子核内
you need other particles called neutrons.
你还需要另一种粒子 称之 中子
Their job is to keep the protons
from getting out of line.
它们的工作是防止质子出轨
They overwhelm the protons
它们用强大的核引力压制质子
A nucleus with two protons is element number two,
原子核有2个质子的元素排名第2
otherwise known as helium.
名曰 氦
A nucleus with six protons is element number six,
原子核有6个质子的元素排名第6
which is carbon,
就是碳
the fundamental building block of life.
生命的基石
The nucleus of a gold atom has 79 protons.
金元素的原子核有79个质子
They attract 79 electrons in clouds around it
在周围的云中 它们吸引了79个电子
The way light interacts with those electrons
光与这些电子的互动
is what makes gold glitter.
就是黄金闪光的原因
Every additional proton in the nucleus
原子核中每增加一个质子
requires enough neutrons to bind them together...
都需要有足够的中子把它们聚集在一起
Up to a point.
在一定程度上
There's an upper limit to the number of neutrons
you can stuff into a nucleus
你能塞进原子核的中子数量是有上限的
before it becomes unstable.
否则会变得不稳定
I know a place
有个地方
where the nuclei of different atoms
不同原子的原子核
actually do touch each other.
能够相互接触
The sun looks like a solid object,
太阳看上去像个实体
but it's not.
但它不是
It's so hot that all its atoms
它把所有的原子都
are always in their gaseous state.
加热到了气态
The bonds that join atoms
to make solids and liquids on earth
地球上将原子束缚产生液态和固体的粘合力
are not strong enough to withstand
the heat of the broiling sun
不足以承受炽热太阳的热量
Those arcing streams of incandescent gas
that dwarf the earth
那些耀眼气体的弧形气流使地球看上去渺小
are guided by magnetic lines of force
that emanate from below the surface of the sun.
受到太阳表面之下发射出来的力场的磁力线引导
Why is the sun so hot?
太阳怎么会这么热
Because its own stupendous gravity
因为它惊人的引力
is squeezing its atoms together.
将原子们积压在一起
The energy of gravity is being transformed
引力的能量转换成
into the energy of moving atoms.
移动原子的能量
That's what heat is.
那就是热的来源
The deeper we go into the sun,
越到太阳的内部
the greater the squeezing
挤压的力量越大
and the higher the temperature.
温度也越高
In the heart of the sun,
在太阳的中心
the atoms are moving so fast that when they collide,
they fuse. Their nuclei touch.
原子的移动速度快到 它们碰撞时发生融化 原子核发生接触
The sun is a nuclear fusion reactor,
太阳就是核聚变反应堆
held together by its own gravity.
由它的引力来维系
It's balanced between the inward pull of gravity
and the outward push of its hot gases.
它在向内拉的引力和向外推的热浪间取得平衡
That balance has lasted billions of years,
这种平衡持续几十亿年
providing stability that made possible
the evolution of life on earth.
提供了使地球上生物进化成为可能的稳定性
In the sun's core,
在太阳的核心
the fusion of hydrogen into helium
氢融合后变成氦
releases nuclear energy in the form of photons.
以光子的形式释放核能
These particles of light
这些光的微粒
slowly work their way to the surface,
慢慢的来到表面
where they're seen as sunlight.
就是我们所见的日光
Helium is the ash of the sun's nuclear furnace.
氦原子就是太阳核反应的残渣
The sun is a medium-sized star.
太阳是一颗中等尺寸的恒星
Its core is only a lukewarm ten million degrees...
它的核心温度只不过1千万度
hot enough to fuse hydrogen,
只够融化氢原子
but too cold to fuse helium.
却不足以融化氦原子
There are many stars in the galaxy
银河系中有很多恒星
that get much hotter,
比太阳热得多
because they're more massive
因为它们质量更大
and have more gravity.
引力更大
Such stars fuse helium into heavier elements,
这些恒星将氦融化成更重的元素
like carbon and oxygen.
比如 碳和氧
In their old age,
等它们老了
they gently diffuse these elements into space.
它们慢慢的将这些元素散播到太空中
Other stars, more massive yet,
还有些恒星 质量更大
live fast and die young
一生苦短 英年早逝
in cataclysmic supernova explosions.
卒于灾难性的超新星大爆炸
In our galaxy, such stars go supernova
我们的银河系中 这样的恒星变成超新星
about once a century.
大约100年一次
These explosions are far hotter than the core of the sun
这些爆炸比太阳核心热的多得多
hot enough to transform elements like iron
热的足够把铁元素
into all the heavier ones
变成更重的元素
and spew them into space.
并把它们喷向太空
The large magellanic cloud
大麦哲伦星云
is a neighboring galaxy of our milky way.
是我们银河系的邻居
It's visible in the skies of the Southern hemisphere.
可以在南半球的星空中看到
When a supernova explodes,
当超新星爆炸时
its brightness rivals
它的亮度超过
that of its entire galaxy.
它的整个星系
But all that light is only about one percent
of the energy liberated in the explosion.
但这些光也只是爆炸产生的能量中的大约1%
The rest of the energy is
carried off by the most common
其它的能量化成宇宙中最常见
and the most mysterious particles in the cosmos.
也最神秘的微粒
There are trillions of them
passing through you right now,
现在就有几万亿的这种微粒穿过你的身体
and yet tracking down even one of them
然而即使为了找到一个这样的微粒
will take us to one of the strangest places on earth.
也需要我们去到地球上最离奇的地方
Stalking the wild neutrino
追踪野生的中微子
is the rarest of sport.
是最小众的运动
The lengths one must go to track them down
is nothing short of astonishing
追踪它们的难度 难得令人惊讶
Welcome to Super Kamiokande,
欢迎来到超级神冈探测器
the subterranean Japanese neutrino detection chamber.
日本地下中微子探测器的内部
We're more than a half mile beneath earth's surface.
我们身处地表之下超过半英里 （大约1公里)
You might ask, "well, who in their right mind
你或许会问 哪个正常人
would bury an astronomical observatory
so far underground?"
会把天文台埋在这么深的地下
Those who hunt the most elusive prey in the cosmos:
这些人狩猎宇宙中最神出鬼没的猎物
The neutrino.
中微子
This enormous array of light detectors
这个庞大的光探测器阵列
surrounding 50,000 tons of distilled water
围绕着5万吨蒸馏水
is a trap designed to catch neutrinos only.
设计这个陷阱只为了抓捕中微子
Other particles, such as cosmic rays...
其他粒子 例如宇宙射线
mostly protons and electrons
that rain down from space...
大部分是从太空中落下的质子和电子
cannot get through all that rock above us.
无法穿过我们头顶的岩石
But matter poses no obstacle to a neutrino.
但这些对中微子来说都不是障碍
A neutrino could pass through 100 light-years of steel
中微子可以穿过100光年厚的铁板
without even slowing down.
甚至不会减速
Neutrinos hardly interact with matter at all
中微子几乎不受其他物质影响
That's why you need so much of it
to catch even one of them.
这就是为什么我们需要如此大费周章
On those rare occasions when a neutrino
在很罕见的情况下
actually does collide with a particle of ordinary matter,
中微子和其他微粒发生冲突
it produces a ghostly, ring-shaped flash of light.
它会产生一个幽灵般的环形闪光
We're lying in wait
我们守株待兔
for a particle that weighs next to nothing.
等一个几乎没有重量的微粒
Even the miniscule electron
甚至比电子
has more than a million times its mass...
还轻100万倍
There!
那里
When the supernova in the large magellanic cloud
blew its top in 1987
1987年 当大麦哲伦星云的超新星爆炸时
this is what it would have looked like in here.
这就是当时这里出现的景象
Now remember, the large magellanic cloud
请记住 大麦哲伦星云
is in our Southern hemisphere,
在我们的南半球
so the neutrinos didn't come through
所以这些中微子不是穿过
that half-mile of rock above us,
我们头顶上半英里的岩石
they had to pass through the thousands of miles
而是必须穿过我们身下
of rock and iron below us to reach this detector.
几千英里的岩石和铁才能到达这里
But the coolest thing
was that those neutrinos
但是最酷的事情是
hit earth three hours before
the light from the supernova did.
中微子比超新星发出的光早3小时到达地球
If nothing can travel faster than light,
如果没有什么能比光跑得快
how could that possibly be?
这又是怎么回事呢
This is a dead star walking.
星之将死
It may look normal, but deep within it
something cataclysmic is happening
看上去好像挺正常 但是在它的深处大灾难已经发生
This blue super giant star
这颗蓝色的超级巨大的恒星
has already begun to explode inside.
内部即将发生爆炸
Like rats deserting
a sinking ship, the neutrinos
如同即将沉船上的老鼠 慌不择路
produced in the heart of the exploding star
即将爆炸的恒星内部产生的中微子
race outward at near the speed of light,
以接近光速的速度向外逃逸
through overlying mass in only a few seconds
几秒内穿过覆盖物
But the shock wave of the exploding gas
但是爆炸气体的冲击波
plods along from the center of the star
从恒星内部缓缓踱出
at 1/10,000 the speed of light
只有光速的万分之一
until it finally reaches
直到最后抵达
the star's surface,
恒星的表面
turning it into supernova 1987a.
变成了1987年的超新星
It took hours for the explosion
要好几个小时
to reach the surface of the star and blow it wide open,
爆炸才能到达表面 然后向外喷发
exposing the super hot core.
将极度炙热的内核炸开
The neutrinos had an insurmountable head start.
中微子已经赢在了起跑线上
That's why the flash of light arrived on earth
so much later than the shower of neutrinos.
这就是为什么闪光会比中微子晚这么多到达地球
Before anyone had ever snared the wild neutrino,
在“野生”中微子被捕获前
it existed in the mind of a theoretical physicist.
它已经存在于理论物理学家的脑海中
Just as Charles Darwin knew
就如同查尔斯·达尔文知道
there must be an extremely long-nosed creature
flying around somewhere in Madagascar
必定有一种超级长鼻生物生活在马达加斯加
a 20th-century physicist named Wolfgang Pauli...
一位名叫沃尔夫冈·泡利的20世纪物理学家
was desperately seeking a particle
致力于寻找一种微粒
to rescue one of the pillars of modern physics,
用来拯救现代物理学的支柱之一
the law of the conservation of energy.
能量守恒定律
So why didn't I flinch?
我为什么没有退缩
Because the laws of science differ fundamentally
from those of other human endeavors
因为科学定律与其它人类活动的根本区别
In order for an idea to become a scientific law,
要将一种设想变成科学定律
it has to unbreakable.
必须要无懈可击
That's why I was willing to bet this face
这就是为何我愿意赌上我的脸
on the laws of conservation of energy.
来证明能量守恒定律
Now, if you try this at home,
如果你在家自己尝试
take care not to give the cannonball a push.
千万小心不要推这个球
That's adding energy,
那会增加能量
and the ball will surely
come back and do some damage.
这球肯定会回来造成伤害
You just have to let it go, like this.
只要像这样轻轻放手
By lifting the ball,
抬起这个球
you give it gravitational energy,
你给它势能
which is the potential
to fall and accelerate.
使它可能坠落并且加速
The cannonball is going fastest
when it's at the bottom of its arc
球在弧度底部时速度达到最大
and at that moment,
在那个时候
it's converted all of its gravitational energy
to the energy of motion.
它把所有的势能转化成动能
As it swings, the cannonball
is constantly exchanging
摇摆时 球不断转换能量
one of these two kinds of energy for the other,
从一种转换到另一种
but the total amount of energy remains constant.
但是能量的总量保持不变
That's an example of the
law of conservation of energy.
这就是能量守恒定律的例子
Once the cannonball is released,
放开球的那刻
it can never gain more energy
than it had to begin with.
它就无法获得更多的能量
It has no way to fly up and break my nose.
它不可能飞过来打到我的鼻子
The energy accounting books
are always strictly balanced.
能量这笔账永远是平衡的
There's no such thing as cheating.
做不得假
So in the 20th century,
在20世纪
when physicists first calculated
the energy of atoms precisely,
当科学家首次精确测量出原子的能量
they were startled to discover
他们惊讶的发现了
an apparent violation of this law.
违背这个定律的情况
They found that in some radioactive atoms,
他们发现在一些放射性原子中
the nucleus can spontaneously eject an electron.
原子核自发的喷出一个电子
This transforms the atom
into a different element.
将原子转变成另一种元素
The physicists were mystified.
物理学家迷惑了
The energy of the escaped electron
逃逸电子的能量
plus that of the new element
加上新元素的能量
adds up to less than the energy
in the original nucleus.
少于原有原子核的能量
But the law says,
定律指出
"thou shall not destroy or create energy."
能量既不会凭空产生 也不会凭空消失
So where did the missing energy go?
那么那些能量去了哪里
In 1930...
1930年
Wolfgang Pauli predicted
沃尔夫冈·泡利预测
there must be an undiscovered particle,
一定有一种未知的微粒
one that makes off with the missing energy.
带走了这些能量
At the time, Pauli lamented
当时 沃尔夫冈·泡利感叹
that such a phantom particle might be so minute,
如此微小的虚幻微粒
swift and evasive
迅速而难以琢磨
as to forever defy detection.
可能永远都探测不到了
But that was a rare failure
of his imagination
好在那只是他罕有的一次错误预测
because science is always searching
因为科学家总是不断
for a way to go deeper still.
寻找探索的新方法
A generation later,
几十年后
Pauli's neutrinos were actually
detected for the first time
中微子第一次被人们探测到
in radiation from a nuclear reactor.
在核反应堆的辐射中
And we've been finding them,
with difficulty, ever since.
虽然很艰难 但从那之后我们不断找到更多的
There are scientists today
如今 有些科学家们
who are trying to find a way to ride those neutrinos
尝试利用那些中微子
all the way back to the beginning of time.
来研究时间的起源
We'll go as far as they have gone
to come up against the wall of forever.
一起去看看他们的成就  那是一面永恒之墙
The wall of forever is nothing new.
永恒之墙并不新鲜
Our ancestors came up against it
我们的祖先也遇到过
almost as soon as they first started imagining it.
几乎就在他们第一次开始想象时
A million dawns ago, in the 13th century bc,
几千年前 公元前13世纪
the Egyptian built this temple at Abu Simbel
埃及人建造了阿布辛贝勒神庙
to honor the Pharaoh Ramses II,
纪念法老王拉美西斯二世
depicted here in four colossal statues.
在这里留下了四座巨大的石像
Reigning even above even this mighty king
is the falcon-headed Ra-Harakhti
在这位伟大君主之上真正的王者其实是鹰首太阳神
God of the sun.
太阳之神
The temple was designed so that
the light from the rising sun
这座神庙被设计成每年只有两次
could only enter the sanctuary
on two days every year.
旭日的霞光金辉才会射入神殿
As the rays enter the temple,
当光线照进神庙
they burnish the statues of the gods
with their golden light
在贯穿整个神殿前
before penetrating the sanctuary.
日光使众神的石像闪耀着金色的光芒
Even then, one God remains in shadow.
但是 仍有一位神的石像依然处在阴影中
Ptah, lord of creation,
普塔 创造之神
as if the origin of the universe
must forever be concealed.
仿佛暗示宇宙的起源注定永远神秘
Feel the sun on your face.
感受阳光照在脸上
The energy that warms you
使你温暖的能量
began its journey some ten million years ago
来自几千万年前
in the heart of the sun.
太阳的核心
Unlike neutrinos,
与中微子不同
the photons needed
质子需要
that long to work their way out
from the core to the surface.
这么久的时间才能从核心到达表面
Why?
为啥
Because they were colliding billions
of times per second with the sun's atoms
因为它们与太阳的原子每秒发生几十亿次的碰撞
every collision sending them off in a random direction.
每次撞击都将它们推向不同的方向
But once they finally reached the surface,
它们一旦到达表面
they were free to dash nonstop, at the speed of light
它们就彻底解放 以光的速度
in a mere eight minutes and 20 seconds
from the sun to you
只用区区8分20秒 就来到你的面前
Ten-million-year-old light on your face.
一千万岁高龄的阳光
What was happening
when that light left the heart of the sun?
当那光离开太阳核心时 又是怎么的景象呢
The cosmic calendar compresses
宇宙年历将宇宙
the entire 13.8 billion year history
整整138亿年的历史
of the universe into a single year.
压缩到一年的时间内
Every month represents about a billion years.
每个月代表10亿年
Every day, about 40 million years.
一天就是4千万年
The universe is so old that,
on the cosmic calendar,
宇宙的历史如此悠久 在年历上
ten million years ago
only takes us back as far as...
1千万年前 也只不过是
6:00 P.M. on the last evening
of the last day of the year
这一年的最后一天的下午6点
And what about us?
那我们呢
Humans had yet to evolve.
人类还没开始进化
Ten million years ago,
1千万年前
our ancestors were anthropoid apes,
我们的祖先还是类人猿
swinging through the trees of Africa.
活跃在非洲的丛林中
To us, ten million years
seems like a long time,
对我们来说 1千万年好像很久远
but it's only the length of an afternoon
但是对于宇宙来说
on the timescale of the cosmos.
那只不过是半天而已
The sun began fusing hydrogen
4,500 million years ago...
45亿年前 太阳开始放出光芒
August 31 on the cosmic calendar.
宇宙历上的8月31号
Our milky way galaxy
我们的银河系
is about 10,000 million years old.
大约100亿岁
The first galaxies formed about
a few billion years earlier.
第一个星系比它还早几十亿年
Something keeps me from going
any further back in time.
有东西阻挡我们回到更远的过去
What is this?
是什么呢
It's the nature of light and time.
是光与时间的本质
Because light travels at a finite speed,
因为光的速度有限
to look across space is to look back in time.
看向宇宙其实看到的是过去的光
So the farther we see,
看的越远
the older the light.
看到的光越古老
This is as far back in the history of
the cosmos as we can see with light.
这是我们所能看到宇宙历史上最古老的光
It's a baby picture of universe,
这是宇宙刚诞生的样子
when it was only 380,000 years old.
只有38万岁
That's 15 minutes into January 1
on the cosmic calendar
宇宙历上最初的15分钟
If we look as far as we can see in any direction
using microwave telescopes
我们用微波望远镜看向宇宙的尽头
this is what we see,
看到的就是这样
the glow left over from the Big Bang.
大爆炸留下的光晕
Imagine that all the matter and energy
of the observable universe
想象一下 可观测宇宙的所有物质和能量
was concentrated into something
no larger than this
都被浓缩成这样的大小
That's the size of the universe
这就是当时宇宙的大小
when it was a trillionth of a trillionth
of a trillionth of a second old
当它只有1.0e-36秒时
All the matter and energy
of the hundred billion galaxies
几千亿个星系的物质与能量
now splayed out across
the billions of light-years
如今扩展到方圆几十亿光年的范围
were once pent up in something the size of a marble
曾经都被禁锢在这个弹珠大小的东西内
Can you imagine how tightly packed
that marble must have been?
你能想象出那颗弹珠有多紧密吗
Far too dense for any kind
of light to move through it,
稠密得使任何光都无法穿过
but no obstacle for the likes of neutrinos.
但这阻碍不了中微子
The big bang must have produced stupendous
numbers of neutrinos,
大爆炸必定产生了数量惊人的中微子
which flew unhindered through
that inconceivable crush of matter
它们顺畅地穿过那些紧密得难以置信的物质
The very thing that makes them
almost impossible to detect
使它们几乎无法被探测的最关键因素是
is what allows neutrinos to sail through the curtain
that conceals the beginning of time
它们可以穿过遮掩时间起源的厚重幕布
Where are they now?
它们在哪里
They are here, they're there,
在这里 在那里
everywhere throughout the universe.
宇宙中无处不在
Neutrinos from creation are within you.
宇宙诞生时中微子就在你的内心深处
From a marble...
从一个弹珠
To the cosmos.
到整个宇宙
This is the road that Thales
and Democritus put us on some 2,500 years ago...
这是一条泰利斯和德谟克利特2500年前带我们走上的路
a road of endless searching,
无尽的探索之路
a relentless, systematic hunt for new worlds
不断地有条不紊地探索新的世界
and an ever-deepening understanding of nature.
并且不断加深对自然的理解
Who among you will pick up that torch
and take us down that next stretch of road?
你们中有人会接过火炬 带领我们走上一条更宽广的大路吗
Sync and corrections by oykubuyuk
www.addic7ed.com
中文翻译： @SaltyEggPain